ILGWU. Oral histories, 5780/110 OHT
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Oral histories
1966-1985
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
5780/110 OHT
7.33 cubic feet
7.3 linear feet
Transcripts
This collection consists of transcripts of oral history interviews with officers, staff, and members of the ILGWU.
6327035
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
July 2011
EAD encoding:
Cheryl Beredo, July 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of transcripts of oral history interviews with officers, staff, and members of the ILGWU.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU Records
5780 OH. ILGWU. Oral history
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Appleton, Shelley; Bachrach, Michael; Borenstein, Sarah; Breslow, Israel; Conticelli, Anthony; Denaro, John; Diamond, Moe; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982.; Faier, Jack; Fedorin, Rose Kaufman; Follman, Benjamin D.; Gatti, Frank; Gingold, David; Goldstein, Eugene; Graeber, Ruth Rubinstein; Gross, Murray; Lanxner, Bertha Mandel; Larsen, Clara; Minkoff, Nathaniel; Newman, Pauline; Novak, Morris; Parenti, Enrico; Pepe, Pauline; Plotkin, Abraham; Reed, Lula; Ross, William; Sandhaus, Samuel; Schindler, Harry; Schlesinger, Emil; Schmidt, Fred; Shane, Bernard; Shrog, Nettie Harary; Shuster, Mary Goff; Silverman, Jennie; Stenzor, Isidor; Stern, Josephine; Stulberg, Louis, 1901-1977; Toper, Lazare; Tyler, Gus; Weiss, Ida; Weiss, Samuel; Wells, David; Zelinka, David; Zimmerman, Charles S., 1896-1983; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
6327035
- Moe Diamond. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  O.H. 1. March 1 and 11, 1974. Pages 1-54
- David Dubinsky. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  O.H. 2. June 25 and July 11, 1974. Pages 1-67
- David Dubinsky. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  O.H. 2. July 24 and August 21, 1974. Pages 68-124
- David Gingold. Interviewed by Gus Tyler, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  O.H. 3. Unedited. February 28 and April 3, 1974. Pages 1-48
- David Gingold. Interviewed by David Wells, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  O.H. 3. Unedited. July 24 and August 22, 1974. Pages 49-110
- David Gingold. Interviewed by David Wells, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  O.H. 3. Unedited. August 28 and December 3, 1974. Pages 111-186
- David Gingold. Interviewed by Gus Tyler and David Wells, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  O.H. 3. February 28, April 3, and July 25, 1974. Pages 1-70
- David Gingold. Interviewed by David Wells, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  O.H. 3. July 25 and August 22, 1974. Pages 71-123
- David Gingold. Interviewed by David Wells, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  O.H. 3. August 28 and December 3, 1974. Pages 124-207
- Pauline Newman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  O.H. 4. December 11, 1973. Pages 1-47
- Emil Schlesinger. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  O.H. 5. Unedited. July 23, 1974
- Emil Schlesinger. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  O.H. 5. Unedited. August 28, 1974
- Emil Schlesinger. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  O.H. 5. Unedited. August 29, 1974
- Emil Schlesinger. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  O.H. 5. July 23 and August 28, 1974. Pages 1-116
- Emil Schlesinger. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  O.H. 5. August 29, 1974. Pages 117-171
- Emil Schlesinger. Verbatim statements, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  O.H. 5. Pages 1-58
- David Zelinka. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  O.H. 6. January 22 and 28 and July 31, 1975. Pages 1-103
- Anthony (Tony) Conticelli. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  O.H. 7. Unedited.
- Anthony (Tony) Conticelli. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  O.H. 7. Unedited
- Anthony (Tony) Conticelli. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  O.H. 7. January 14 and 22, February 12 and 25, and April 16, 1975. Pages 1-155
- Anthony (Tony) Conticelli. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  O.H. 7. January 14 and 22, February 12 and 25, and April 16, 1975. Pages 156-310
- Isidore Stenzor. Autobiographical sketch, Biographical notes on over a half century of a stormy but interesting and rewarding life. Los Angeles, California, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  O.H. 8. No tape available. June 1974. 54 pages
- David Dubinsky. Recorded interview by Pat Daniels, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  O.H. 9. No tape available. December 13, 1966. Pages 1-39
- William Ross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  O.H. 10. May 26 and 27, 1975. Pages 1-64
- William Ross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  O.H. 10. May 27 and June 1, 1975. Pages 65-129
- William Ross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  O.H. 10. June 1, 1975. Pages 130-175
- William Ross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  O.H. 10. June 1 and 21, 1975. Pages 176-233
- William Ross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  O.H. Unedited. May 26 and 27, 1975
- William Ross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  O.H. 10. Unedited. June 1 and 21, 1975
- Samuel Sandhaus. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  O.H. 11. March 24 and April 30, 1975. Pages 1-95
- Louis Stulberg. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  O.H. 12. December 11, 18 and 24, 1975, and January 8 and 29, 1976. Pages 1-191
- Louis Stulberg. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  O.H. 12. January 29, February 2, and April 26, 1976. Pages 192-262
- Louis Stulberg. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  O.H. 12. May 17 and July 22, 1976. Pages 263-331
- Louis Stulberg. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  O.H. 12. July 22 and 29, September 22, 1976. Pages 332-404
- Bernard Shane. Autobiographical Sketch, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  O.H. 13. Pages 1-92
- Josephine Stern. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  O.H. 14. July 10, 1976. Pages 1-32.
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  O.H. 15. November 5 and 12, December 11 and 23, 1975; June 4, July 1 and 28, September 20, October 14, November 8 and 18, 1976; March 17, 24, and 30, April 14 and 20, May 5 and 16, July 6 and 12, 1977; January 5 and 9, April 8 and 24, May 2, 6 and 23, Ju
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1978-1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interview with Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1976-1977 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Charles Zimmerman. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1978-1980 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Murray Gross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  O.H. 16. April 6, 1977 (closed). Pages 1-44
- Murray Gross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  O.H. 16. April 11 and 20, 1977. Pages 60-180
- Murray Gross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  O.H. 16. May 3, 1977. Pages 181-230
- Murray Gross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  O.H. 16. May 10, 1977. Pages 231-280
- Murray Gross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  O.H. 16. June 21, 1977. Pages 281-322
- Murray Gross. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  O.H. 16. July 20 and 26, 1977. Pages 323-406
- Enrico Parenti. Interviewed by Harvey Gold, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  O.H. 17. July 3, 1974. Pages 1-51
- Bertha Mandel Lanxner. Interviewed by William Lanxner, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  O.H. 18. September 2, 1978. Pages 1-26
- Abraham Plotkin. Autobiographical Chronicle, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  O.H. 19. Los Angeles, California, August 1977-January 1979. Pages 1-82
- Abraham Plotkin. Autobiographical chronicle, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  O.H. 19. Los Angeles, California, August 1977-January 1979. Pages 83-163
- Abraham Plotkin. Autobiographical chronicle, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  O.H. 19. Los Angeles, California, August 1977-January 1979. Pages 164-273
- Abraham Plotkin. Autobiographical chronicle, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  O.H. 19. Los Angeles, California, August 1977-January 1979. Pages 274-342
- Abraham Plotkin. Autobiographical chronicle, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  O.H. 19. Los Angeles, California, August 1977-January 1979. Pages 343-471
- Abraham Plotkin. Autobiographical chronicle, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  O.H. 19. Los Angeles, California, August 1977-January 1979. Pages 472-588
- Abraham Plotkin. Autobiographical chronicle, 1977-1979 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  O.H. 19. Los Angeles, California, August 1977-January 1979. Page 590-693
- Abraham Plotkin. Autobiographical chronicle, 1977-1979 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  O.H. 19. Los Angeles, California, August 1977-January 1979. Pages 694-792
- Abraham Plotkin. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund and Ethel Goldwasser, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  O.H. 19. November 6, 8, and 14, 1978.
- Abraham Plotkin. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund and Ethel Goldwasser, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  O.H. 19. November 6, 8, 9, 13 and 14, 1978
- Abraham Plotkin. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund and Ethel Goldwasser, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Frank Gatti. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  O.H. 20. October 2, 9, 16, 23, November 20 and 29, and December 4, 1979. Pages 1-150
- Frank Gatti. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  O.H. 20. October 2, 9, 16, 23, November 20 and 29, and December 4, 1979. Pages 151-259
- Shelley Appleton. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  O.H. 21. October 17, 1979. Pages 1-42
- Samuel Weiss. Statement (in Yiddish) on the "Rescue Campaign" of the International in settling the rescued victims of Nazism and employing them in the women's garment industry, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  O.H. 22. January 1981. Pages 1-21
- Lazare Teper. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  O.H. 23. April 13 and 14, June 16, August 26, September 2, October 28, 1981; January 20, 1982; November 13 and 20, December 5, 11, 18, 1984. The last three hours of interviews are not transcribed. Pages 1-53
- Lazare Teper. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  O.H. 23. April 13 and 14, June 16, August 26, September 2, October 28, 1981; January 20, 1982; November 13 and 20, December 5, 11, 18, 1984. The last three hours of interviews are not transcribed. Pages 55-175
- Lazare Teper. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  O.H. 23. April 13 and 14, June 16, August 26, September 2, October 28, 1981; January 20, 1982; November 13 and 20, December 5, 11, 18, 1984. The last three hours of interviews are not transcribed. Pages 176-262
- Lazare Teper. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  O.H. 23. April 13 and 14, June 16, August 26, September 2, October 28, 1981; January 20, 1982; November 13 and 20, December 5, 11, 18, 1984. The last three hours of interviews are not transcribed. Pages 263-342
- Lazare Teper. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  O.H. 23. April 13 and 14, June 16, August 26, September 2, October 28, 1981; January 20, 1982; November 13 and 20, December 5, 11, 18, 1984. The last three hours of interviews are not transcribed. Pages 343-437
- Lazare Teper. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  O.H. 23. April 13 and 14, June 16, August 26, September 2, October 28, 1981; January 20, 1982; November 13 and 20, December 5, 11, 18, 1984. The last three hours of interviews are not transcribed. Pages 438-529
- Lazare Teper. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  O.H. 23. April 13 and 14, June 16, August 26, September 2, October 28, 1981; January 20, 1982; November 13 and 20, December 5, 11, 18, 1984. The last three hours of interviews are not transcribed. Pages 530-598
- Israel Breslow. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  O.H. 24. June 29, July 13, and August 25, 1981. Pages 1-94
- Israel Breslow. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  O.H. 24. September 1 and 9, 1981. Pages 95-143
- Israel Breslow. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  O.H. 24. October 6, 14, and 20, 1981. Pages 144-277
- Israel Breslow. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  O.H. 24. October 27 and November 10, 1981. Pages 278-355
- Israel Breslow. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  O.H. 24. February 23 and March 2, 1982. Pages 356-426
- Israel Breslow. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  O.H. 24. March 9 and 16, June 1, 1982
- Israel Breslow. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  O.H. 24. June 8, 15 and 29, July 13, and August 17, 1982. Pages 529-698
- Sarah Borenstein. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  O.H. 25. June 9 and 15, 1982. Pages 1-45
- Mary Goff Shuster. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  O.H. 26. September 15, 1982. Pages 1-40
- Jennie Silverman. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  O.H.27. November 24, 1982. Pages 1-49
- Clara Larsen. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  O.H. 28. December 8 and 16, 1982. Pages 1-84
- Joseph Roth. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  O.H. 29. May 4, 1983. Pages 1-40
- John Denaro. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  O.H. 30. May 5 and June 16, 1983. Pages 1-116
- Michael Bachrach. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  O.H. 31. June 14, 1983. Pages 1-39
- Jack Faier. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  O.H. 32. December 22, 1983. Pages 1-29
- Ruth Rubenstein Graeber. Interviewed by Ethel Goldwasser., 1983-1985 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  O.H. 35. December 7, 1983 and April 15, 1985. Pages 1-24
- Morris Novik. Interviewed by Henoch Mendelsund and Bob Parmet (Box 15, Folder 9)
  O.H. 36. November 28, 1984 and May 30 and June 18, 1985.